Problem
One difference between a write-through cache and a write-back cache can be in the time it takes to write. During the first cycle, we detect whether a hit will occur, and during the second (assuming a hit) we actually write the data. Let’s assume that 50% of the blocks are dirty for a write-back cache. For this question, assume that the write buffer for the write through will never stall the CPU (no penalty). Assume a cache read hit takes 1 clock cycle, the cache miss penalty is 50 clock cycles, and a block write from the cache to main memory takes 50 clock cycles. Finally, assume the instruction cache miss rate is 0.5% and the data cache miss rate is 1%. Assuming that on average 26% and 9% of instructions in the workload are loads and stores, respectively, estimate the performance of a write-through cache with a two-cycle write versus a write-back cache with a two-cycle write.


Solution
CPU performance equation: CPUTime = IC ∗ CPI ∗ ClockTime
CPI = CPIexecution + StallCyclesPerInstruction We know:
Instruction miss penalty is 50 cycles
Data read hit takes 1 cycle
Data write hit takes 2 cycles
Data miss penalty is 50 cycles for write through cache
Data miss penalty is 50 cycles or 100 cycles for write back cache
Miss rate is 1% for data cache (MRD) and 0.5% for instruction cache (MRI)
50% of cache blocks are dirty in the write back cache
26% of all instructions are loads 9% of all instructions are stores Then:
CPIexecution = 0.26 ∗ 1 + 0.09 ∗ 2 + 0.65 ∗ 1 = 1.09
Write through
StallCyclesPerInstruction = MRI ∗ 50 + MRD ∗ (0.26 ∗ 50 + 0.09 ∗ 50) = 0.425 so:
	CPI = 1.09 + 0.425 = 1.515	(3)
Write back
StallCyclesPerInstruction = MRI ∗ 50 + MRD ∗ (0.26 ∗ (0.5 ∗ 50 + 0.5 ∗ 100) + 0.09 ∗
(0.5 ∗ 50 + 0.5 ∗ 100)) = 0.5125 so:
	CPI = 1.09 + 0.5125 = 1.6025	(4)
Comparing 3 and 4 we notice that the system with the write back cache is 6% slower.

