Problem
Consider a computer system with a first-level data cache with the following characteristics: size: 16KBytes; associativity: direct-mapped; line size: 64Bytes; addressing: physical.
The system has a separate instruction cache and you can ignore instruction misses in this problem. This system is used to run the following code:
for (i=0; i<4096; i++)
X[i] = X[i] * Y[i] + C
Assume that both X and Y have 4096 elements, each consisting of 4 bytes (single precision floating point). These arrays are allocated consecutively in physical memory. The assembly code generated by a naive compiler is the following:
loop: lw f2, 0(r1)	# load X[i] lw f4, 0(r2)	# load Y[i]
multd f2, f2, f4 # perform the multiplication
addd f2, f2, f0	# add C (in f0)
sw 0(r1), f2	# store the new value of X[i]
addi r1, r1, 4	# update address of X
addi r2, r2, 4	# update address of Y
addi r3, r3, 1	# increment loop counter
bne r3, 4096, loop # branch back if not done
a.	How many data cache misses will this code generate? Breakdown your answer into thethree types of misses. What is the data cache miss rate?
b.	Provide a software solution that significantly reduces the number of data cache misses.How many data cache misses will your code generate? Breakdown the cache misses into the three types of misses. What is the data cache miss rate?
c.	Provide a hardware solution that significantly reduces the number of data cache misses.You are free to alter the cache organization and/or the processor. How many data cache misses will your code generate? Breakdown the cache misses into the three types of misses. What is the data cache miss rate?




Solution
a.
Misses:
coldmisses : 2 ∗ (4096/16) = 512
as every 16th iteration will miss on the load to X and to Y, for the first time conflictmisses : 4096 + (15/16) ∗ 4096 = 4096 + 3840 = 7936
as every store to X will miss because it was displaced by the previous load to Y, and as every load to the remaining 15 elements of Y in a line will miss because they were displaced by the previous store to X total : 512 + 7936 = 8448 misses
So:
missrate : 8448/12288 = 0.6875 (68.75%)
as there are 3 ∗ 4096 = 12288 memory references in the loop
b.
•	alternative 1: merge arrays X and Y, interleaving their elements, now 8 elements of each array fit in the same line coldmisses : 4096/8 = 512 as every 8th iteration will miss on the load to X conflictmisses : 0 total : 512 misses
So:
missrate : 512/12288 = 0.0417 (4.17%)
•	alternative 2: separate arrays X and Y in memory by a distance not multiple of 16K coldmisses : 2 ∗ (4096/16) = 512 as every 16th iteration will miss on the load to X and on the load to Y conflictmisses : 0 total : 512 misses
So:
missrate : 512/12288 = 0.0417 (4.17%)
c.
•	alternative 1: double the cache size to 32KB coldmisses : 2 ∗ (4096/16) = 512
as every 16th iteration will miss on the load to X and on the load to Y conflictmisses : 0 total : 512 misses So:
missrate : 512/12288 = 0.0417 (4.17%)
•	alternative 2: make the cache set associative coldmisses : 2 ∗ (4096/16) = 512
as every 16th iteration will miss on the load to X and on the load to Y conflictmisses : 0 total : 512 misses So:
missrate : 512/12288 = 0.0417 (4.17%)
•	alternative 3: increase the block size by z times coldmisses : 4096/(16 ∗ z)
as every 16*z’th iteration will miss on the load to X (in the limit we use 16KByte lines and the have only a single cold miss) conflictmisses : 2 ∗ 4096 = 8192
as every load to Y will cause a conflict with the just-loaded line of X and every store to X will cause a conflict with the just-loaded line of Y
•	alternative 4: add a next-line prefetcher coldmisses : 2 ∗ (4096/32) = 256
in effect, the next-line prefetcher cuts the cold misses in 2 (each cold miss eliminates the very next cold miss).
conflictmisses : 4096 + (31/32) ∗ 4096 = 8064 So:
missrate : (256 + 8064)/12288 = 0.667 (66.7%)
Note that a streaming prefetcher would eliminate all but the first cold miss on each of the arrays.
•	alternative 5: add a victim cache coldmisses : 4096/16 = 256
as every 16th iteration will miss on the load to X (the other 15 iterations reuse the line left over from the store to X) conflictmisses : 4096
as every load to Y will cause a conflict with the just loaded line of X (the stores to X now hit in the victim cache) total : 256 + 4096 = 4352 misses
So: missrate : 4352/12288 = 0.3542 (35.42%)

